Database, Data, BI, AI, Analytics Data Driven Performance Analyst

# Brian P. Flynn Erie, CO

Product Management & Leadership Development, Architecture

<u>brianpaulflynn@outlook.com</u> *last updated 1/1/2023*http://www.linkedin.com/in/brianpaulflynn

#### **OBJECTIVE**

Obtain a technical leadership position utilizing over twenty-five years of practical experience and education.

### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

Growth Mindset! Architect, People & Product Manager. Former SQL Server expert gone cloud. Passion for innovation. A data driven visionary at the intersection of business, technology and user experience. Possesses well rounded, sharp technical skills, balanced by strong emotional intelligence. Strategically progressive change agent and entrepreneurial leader who enjoys new challenges and seeks to integrate the sum of his experiences into one role for maximum impact. Dabbled in self-employment and discovered a passion for Product Management. Interested in the burgeoning fields of Big Data, Cloud Technology and Analytics. Technical concentrations in Microsoft technology, particularly Azure, Databases, Data Warehousing, Business Intelligence. Complimented with strong understandings of all data center functions e.g. storage, networking, security, virtualization etc. Azure, AWS, & OCI.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Guidehouse (acquired Dovel & Ace Info Solutions): May 2021 - Present

#### Data & Solution Architect

- Consulted teams with strict government restrictions such as FedRAMP, to design solutions for crop insurance programs.
- o Offered Azure, AWS, Okta and SQL experience to multiple projects as directed.
- Built a tool for managing DevOps with PostgreSQL to replace SQL Server in projects.
- o Built proof of concept digital twin work in Azure and AWS using click-ops and IaaC.
- Consulted teams with strict government restrictions such as FedRAMP, to design solutions for crop insurance programs.
- o Provided database solutions for the Production Validator Application project.
- Provided database and web solutions for the Tobacco Processing Application projects.
- Provided production post mortem analysis for SQL Server environments, as required.
- Offered AWS and SQL experience to planning meetings for AWS migrations.
- Offered Azure and SQL experience to a migration from Dynaics CRM to Dynamics 365.
- o Digital Twin and AIML proof of concepts using Terraform, Bash, Azure, AWS, Python.

Imagine Communications Corp, Denver CO: September 2019 - May 2021

## • Infrastructure Architect

- o Multi-Cloud system design, implementation, and support.
- o Azure, AWS, Oracle Cloud.
- o Terraform, CLI, and bash console interface.
- WireGuard VPN
- Windows & Linux environments

Long View Systems, Denver CO: October 2018 - September 2019

### • Solutions Architect

- o Azure cloud consulting e.g. IaaS/PaaS & SQL Server
- o Contributed to Offering for Windows & SQL 2008 End of Support
- o Assessments & Migrations e.g. Movere, Azure Migrate, Azure Site Recovery, etc.
- Hybrid cloud configurations e.g. site to site VPN, IaaS & PaaS
- A hybrid Skype migration, including cloud PBX

o Pre-Sales engagements & Remote support

RSM, Denver CO: May 2017 - October 2018

### Senior Associate

- o Cloud consulting e.g. Azure, Office 365, Citrix, SQL Server, etc.
- Hybrid cloud configurations e.g. site to site VPN
- o Building new environments & migrating from old to new
- o Troubleshooting hybrid cloud solution performance
- o Client visits & Remote support

10-4 Systems Boulder CO: April 2016 - January 2017

# Principal Data Architect

- Responsible to identify a plan to migrate from SQL Server Enterprise to Azure SQL DB
- Responsible for some project management in migrating to Azure
- Responsible for performance troubleshooting of production system
- Responsible for analysis of current architecture issues
- o Responsible for prescribing system modifications
- o Operational support for SQL 2014/2016 and PaaS Azure SQL Server & IaaS SQL Server
- Coached developers in database performance
- o Database source control with GitHub, Visual Studio, & RedGate tools

Solarwinds, formerly Confio (Research & Development) Boulder CO: September 2013 – January 2016

#### • Product Manager

- o Responsible for Database Performance Analyzer Product
- Technology Used : SQL Server, .NET, and Java
- o Research product market opportunities, and interfacing customers
- o Technical product demonstrations and installations
- Work with developers, QA and company thought leaders
- Write technical specifications and road maps
- Prioritize work for development and QA

Scottrade (Information Technology) St. Louis, MO: February 2011 - August 2013

# Database Development Manager

- o Technology Used: SQL Server
- o Manage a team of 25 SQL Server professionals.
- o Responsible for all activities related to database development.
- Provide leadership and influence in the development of Scottrade systems.
- Accountable for the performance and results of 3 application team(s), staff allocation/direction, and the supervision of team members.
- Works with the Application Architects and Project Managers on strategic and tactical projects.
- Works with Project Managers and QA on resource leveling requirements.
- o Performs HR processes (quarterly reviews, yearly reviews, etc.).
- Facilitates and/or monitors periodic code reviews.
- Attends various IS related meetings (e.g. Change Management, project, task, PMO, etc.).
- Schedules and facilitates appropriate team meetings.
- o Facilitates overall coordination, status reporting, and stability of projects.
- Coordinates training within team (internal and external).

- Coaches and develops multiple software developers and supervisors (including exempt and non-exempt resources).
- Monitors production issues on an ad hoc basis to maintain understanding of product stability and assess issue trends.
- o Participates in enhancement, issue, and project prioritization with PMO.
- o Recruits, interviews, and hires additional development staff.
- Develops and maintains effective partnerships with Scottrade product development and business teams in order to understand and anticipate their needs, the business environment, other challenges and opportunities.

## BAT Technology Services (Hosting and Development) St. Louis MO: September 1997 - August 2013

#### Owner

- Launched business that provides hosting, development and software services to small businesses who desire professional grade outsourced services without incurring costs internally.
- Consult with clients and manage projects with 4 developers and 1 graphic designer.
- Responsible for server/network design, maintenance, back-ups, rollouts, troubleshooting, support software licensing and billing.
- o Manage class C network for 240 domains, client and site to site VPN tunnel access.
- Hosted services under various conditions from 4 locations, managing migrations each time.
- o Implmented 6 Small Business Server 2003 environments, performed several swing migrations and a consolidation.
- o Successfully recovered SQL, Exchange and Active Directory databases.

## Gateway EDI (Information Technology) St. Louis MO: November 2006 - February 2011

### • Web Systems Team Supervisor September 2010 - February 2011

- o Technology Used: IIS, ASP.NET, WCF, MVC, SOAP, SQL Server
- Responsible for providing focus and strategy to an area of rapidly growing demand, defining future road maps, staffing, mentoring and communicating vision.
- Manage a team of 3 web technology professionals.
- Led technical teams to resolve capacity issues that eluded them for over a year.
- o Identified key performance metrics and a system to track them.

## • **System Administration Supervisor** September 2008 - September 2010

- Responsible for data center, operations, administration, strategic planning, seeking innovative solutions, shaping technology road map, planning and adhering to budgets, policies, procedures, recruiting high end talent, developing high potential talent, prioritizing and balancing resources with initiatives.
- o Grew team to 8 administrators and 4 desktop support technicians.
- Virtualized 90% of data center, several desktops and constructed fully functional DR site.
- Lead Business Intelligence technical initiatives resulting in creation of a Data Warehousing department.
- Initiated a SharePoint Steering Committee and assigned an administrator to lead meetings.
- Empowered departments to create SharePoint sites and fostered a culture of selfreliance.
- Implemented network and data security systems; maintained HIPAA & EHNAC compliance.

## • System Administration Group Lead May 2008 - September 2008

- Responsible for a team of 3 administrators and 3 desktop support technicians.
- o Implemented a measurable, reportable, easy to use, email based workflow system.

Implemented SharePoint, Reporting Services and Team Foundation Server.

### • System Administration Team: Database Administrator November 2006 - May 2008

- Responsible for server administration, 24/7 support and senior level programming deliverables.
- o Implemented system for logging and analyzing database resource activity.
- Consolidated 4 legacy SQL 2000 servers into SQL 2005 high availability cluster.
- Advised best practices to development teams.
- Responsible for 15 TB of data spread across 300 databases and 5 servers.

Stifel Nicolaus (Information Technology) St. Louis MO: July 2002 - November 2006

## System Engineer : Database Administrator, Web Administrator

- Manage the projects of, train and mentor junior administrator/developer.
- Provide technical consulting to business subject matter experts; mentor the programming of junior developers to accomplish team goals in highly dynamic environment.
- Lead junior developers in BI (creating and supporting data warehouses, data scrubbing procedures, SSAS cubes), intranet tools and reports to provide drill down self-service information access.
- Responsible for server administration, 24/7 support and senior level programming deliverables.
- Manage and develop the production of SQL and Web environments for 1.5+ TB of data spread across 150+ databases on 6+ SQL servers and 6+ IIS servers to include maintenance, standards, rollouts and permissions.
- Design, configure and maintain SQL and Web clusters providing high availability and redundancy.
- o Created self-healing automated processes to reduce need for use of human capital.
- Manage and develop server monitoring systems that send out pages and emails when unexpected errors occur.
- o Developed system for logging and analyzing database resource activity.
- Managed Microsoft Internet Security & Acceleration Firewall.

Huttig Building Products (Information Technology) St. Louis MO: May 1999 - May 2002

## • Web Developer, Database Developer

- Responsible for requirements gathering, lead design, lead development and support for in house developed sql driven web applications.
- Trained and lead junior developer on sql driven web application development projects, directing assignments and mentoring programming skills with fast learning results.
- Designed, developed and maintained public web sites, intranets and in house developed web applications that increased process efficiency by relieving HR staff of multiple manual processes that created audit trails, self-service reporting and collaborative process flow/tracking applications.
- Designed graphics and HTML to dress e-commerce and auction web application interfaces.

Saint Louis University (Information Technology : Student Worker) St. Louis MO : Various time frames

## • Web Design Instructor June - August 1997 & 1998

- Responsible for planning and implementing daily classes.
- Designed and delivered a computer camp curriculum that successfully captured the interests of middle school and early high school age children resulting in 50% enrollment increase.

- Computer Technician August 1995 May 1997
  - o Responsible for Software/Hardware installation, configuration, and troubleshooting.
  - Manned computer lab, performed troubleshooting for undergrad and medical campus faculty and staff.

Edison Brothers (Information Technology: Intern) St. Louis MO: September 1997 - May 1998

#### • Computer Technician

- o Responsible for software/hardware installation, configuration, and troubleshooting.
- Created a batch to build and configure new computer increasing speed ten-fold enabling Windows 95 rollout team to regain time lost due to unforeseen circumstances that would have delayed the project several months.

#### **SKILLS & KNOWLEDGE SUMMARY**

OLTP Databases: T-SQL, Stored Procedures, Triggers, Cursors, Data Modeling, Indexes, Optimization BI/OLAP: SSIS, SSAS, SSRS, Star Schema, Snowflake Schema, Cubes, MDX, Pivot Tables Programming: ASP.NET, VB.NET, C#, React, Powershell, JavaScript, Python, Terraform, Ansible Application Services: SQL Server, Internet Information Server (IIS), SharePoint, Exchange Server High Availability & Scalability: Microsoft Clustering Service (MSCS), Network Load Balancing (NLB)

Windows: Servers (2019,2016,2012,2008,2003), Desktops (11,10,8,7,Vista,XP)

Strategy: Agile Methodology, Service Orientated Architecture (SOA)

Storage & Networking: RAID, SAN, NAS, Firewalls, Routing, TCP/IP, NAT, PAT, VPN, DHCP, DNS

Network Security: Active Directory, Group Policy, Juniper/Netscreen, SonicWall, RADIUS

Cloud: Azure, AWS, OCI, IaaS, PaaS, IaC, DevOps

#### **EDUCATION**

Saint Louis University St. Louis, MO: B.A. Computer Science Major, Mathematics Minor: Cum Laude

<u>**Davisbase**</u> Saint Louis, MO: Agile Boot Camp

Pragmatic Works Saint Louis, MO: Power Pivot for Techies

Microsoft Saint Louis, MO: Visual Studio 2010 ALM: Team Foundation Server Administration

Gateway EDI Human Resources St. Louis, MO: Emotional Intelligence For Personal Leadership

**AAIM Employers Association** St. Louis, MO: Supervisory Certification

**<u>Dale Carnegie</u>** St. Louis, MO: Leadership Training for Managers

LRS Education Services Springfield, IL: Course 2074A: Designing and Implementing OLAP Solutions

#### **RECOMENDATIONS VIA LINKED-IN**

"Brian understands technology, what problems customers need to solve, and how to build great products. He is passionate about what he does and always gives 110%. During the past two years I have learned a lot from him and have received from Brian many ideas and recommendations to make our products and our marketing better. I have no hesitation in recommending Brian as a technology professional, database expert, product manager, and a great guy to work with."

— Gerardo Dada, VP, Product Marketing and Strategy, Solarwinds (indirect manager)

"Brian's leadership style is a mix of Intuition and Intellect. I've worked for Managers who rely on one \*or\* the other with mixed results. Brian uses both with very strong results. This together with an overall positive demeanor enable him to effectively manage his team through a great variety of situations of varying complexity. I've worked for Brian as a consultant in various contexts and have found him to be consistent in the use of his style."

- Rich Quinn, Consultant, Gateway EDI and BAT Technology Services (direct report)

"Brian worked for me for a few years as a Supervisor, both for my SysAdmin and Web Services Team. He possess VERY strong technical skills, is an excellent problem solver, and did a very good job as a Supervior. He added value to whatever department or project he was involved in. He will be missed."

— Dave Cheli, CIO, Gateway EDI (manager)

"During the year I worked with Brian at Gateway EDI, he displayed great versatility. When I started, he supervised our DBAs. Brian is very knowledgeable in databases and I often consulted him on database related questions and issues. He then switchhed to supervising the web services group and quickly came up to speed on our web development platform and applications. Brian is very personable. He's a great mediator and has a knack for difussing tense situations. I enjoyed working with Brian and appreicated his expertise."

- Brian Lawrence, IT Manager, Gateway EDI (colleague)

"Simply put, Brian is one of the best managers I have ever had the pleasure of reporting to. He not only gave me the freedom to work on the things that I felt would improve the security of the way we did business at Gateway EDI, but he did so in a way that gave me the confidence that was needed in that position. Always backing my play provided I had done my research and had given him the reasoning for the project at hand. Brian is always willing to listen to a strong argument and gives those he works with the chance to voice their opinion before drawing his own conclusion. In short, he always did what a manager SHOULD do. He leaned on those that he trusted for their technical background to make correct decisions.... Excellent trait that is not often found in a manager! I would not hesitate to work with him again should our career paths ever meet again."

— Matt Sheaver, Network Security Engineer, Gateway EDI (direct report)

"Although Brian was not part of the actual group that I was in I had the pleasure of interacting with him on a number of occasions on several projects. He was always able to focus directly upon the hot spots in the work that we did, in some cases providing expert guidance and in others pinpointing the most critical areas with aplomb. He was always at the top of his game and always pleasant to work with. I'd heartily recommend him for any technical leadership position."

— Tom Jorgenson, Sr. Developer, Gateway EDI (colleague)

"I worked with Brian on a large sharepoint project; Brian's innovation and creativity helped dispatch a message to others in our company with great sucess. Any time I hear that Brian is heading up a

project or task, I have the utmost confidence that it will be completed with accuracy and integrity."

— Mike Parisi, Sales - Supervisor, Gateway EDI (colleague)

"Brian is an excellent systems engineer with wonderful technical skills. Anytime I gave Brian a project, I knew that it would be completed at the highest level possible. Brian constantly worked with his co-workers to explain systems that he worked on and to share his wealth of knowledge. From the time that I have met Brian, he has always been able to work with everyone and has had the ability to manage others. I've also had the fortune to work with Brian outside of Stifel Nicolaus and have always found him to be extremely professional with co-workers and clients."

— Mike Payne, Network Manager, Stifel Nicolaus, managed Brian at Stifel Nicolaus

"Brian brings a highly creative and skilled approach to the workplace. When Brian reported to me, he headed the development of our company's Intranet site. Brian's drive for perfection and creative style allowed us to create a tool set for over 2,000 employees that would still rival web sites I've seen 8 years since. His talent and passion for success makes him a highly attractive candidate for any employer needing his talents."

Kenneth Morrill, Director of eBusiness, HUTTIG Building Products (manager)

"Brian worked with the Human Resources department to develop an in-house benefit enrollment system. He not only had the technical skills to build an easy to use site for all level of employees but he was able to interact and communicate easily with the HR department in determining what was needed to build the system without using IT technical terms and not making the user feel inadequate. He was very detail-oriented and communicated well with coworkers."

— Karen Tauchert, Manager, Benefits and Compensation, Huttig Building Products, worked with Brian at Huttig Building Products

REFERENCES AVAILABLE UPON REQUEST